<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>motd</title>
<link>https://srirangav.github.io/motd/</link>
<description>Message of the day</description>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 13:43:48 PST</lastBuildDate>
<item>
<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 00:00:00 PST</pubDate>
<link>https://srirangav.github.io/motd/2024/01/index.html#6f1ad4197be6b1346be6ec725c61af5a</link>
<title>Cephid variables probably not responsible for the Hubble tension</title>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<pre>Cephid variables probably not responsible for the Hubble tension:

<a href="https://phys.org/news/2024-01-astronomers-explanation-hubble-tension.html">https://phys.org/news/2024-01-astronomers-explanation-hubble-tension.html</a>

&#34;In this new study, the team looked at more than a
thousand Cepheid variables and was able to pinpoint the
distance relation for Cepheids with extreme precision.
From this, they proved that Cepheid variable error can&#39;t
account for the Hubble tension.&#34;

</pre>]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 00:00:00 PST</pubDate>
<link>https://srirangav.github.io/motd/2024/01/index.html#1c4f14f2467d158fedb635e5c50f100e</link>
<title>The 18% O2 solution</title>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<pre>The 18% O2 solution:

<a href="https://bigthink.com/13-8/oxygen-bottleneck/">https://bigthink.com/13-8/oxygen-bottleneck/</a>

&#34;Drawing on experiments carried out across disciplines as
varied as combustion engineering to biogeochemistry, we
found that an atmosphere with anything less than 18%
oxygen would not allow open-air combustion. Remarkably,
for most of our planet&#39;s 4.5-billion-year history, Earth&#39;s
oxygen levels have been way, way below 18%.  In fact, only
over the past 500 million years or so has the atmosphere
held enough oxygen for anything to freely burn in the open
air.

Why does any of this matter? Imagine a young and
intelligent species on an alien world with an atmosphere
that&#39;s just 1% oxygen. Those clever tool-using creatures
would never get the chance to watch a tree burn after
being hit by lightning and get the idea of using fire for
their own purposes. They would never have the chance to
learn how fire could be used to cook food, clear land, or,
most importantly, melt metals. The poverty of oxygen in
their air would likely box these creatures in forever,
limiting their development.&#34;

</pre>]]>
</description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
